阿尔法小分队荣誉译制
翻：@ErrorEnvyEnchant 校：@Auriance 压制：@Mihael_Ho
长期招募 详情见微博置顶@阿尔法小分队科教组
大家好 我是凯莉·安 欢迎来到计算机速成课
Hi, I'm Carrie Anne and welcome to Crash Course Computer Science!
一系列讲到 计算机取得了很大的进步
As we've discussed throughout the series, computers have come a long way
从也许一秒一次计算的机械装置
from mechanical devices capable of maybe one calculation per second,
到以kHz GHz运行的CPU
to CPUs running at kilohertz and megahertz speeds.
你现在在看这个视频的设备肯定以大约
The device you're watching this video on right now is almost certainly running
GHz的速度运行 也就是每秒执行数十亿的指令
at Gigahertz speed - that's billions of instructions executed every second.
相信我 这绝对是庞大的计算
Which, trust me, is a lot of computation!
早期的电子计算机中处理器通常是通过
In the early days of electronic computing, processors were typically made faster
提高芯片中晶体管的转换时间来提高速度的
by improving the switching time of the transistors inside the chip
芯片是由逻辑门 ALU
- the ones that make up all the logic gates, ALUs
和其他东西组成 这些在前面几集谈到过
and other stuff we've talked about over the past few episodes.
但是仅仅加快晶体管的速度也远远不够
But just making transistors faster and more efficient only went so far,
所以处理器设计者发明了多种提升性能的技巧
so processor designers have developed various techniques to boost performance allowing
不仅仅是使得简单的指令运行的快
not only simple instructions to run fast,
更加复杂的运算也能运行
but also performing much more sophisticated operations.
上一集中我们给CPU写了一段小程序让我们能相除两个数
Last episode, we created a small program for our CPU that allowed us to divide two numbers.
我们通过多次连续的减法达到目的 比如16除以4
We did this by doing many subtractions in a row... so, for example, 16 divided by 4
就可以分解为更小的问题 16减4 减4 减4 减4
could be broken down into the smaller problem of 16 minus 4, minus 4, minus 4, minus 4.
当我们得到零 或者负数时就表明完成了
When we hit zero, or a negative number, we knew that we we're done.
但是这个方法消耗了大量时钟周期 也极其不高效
But this approach gobbles up a lot of clock cycles, and isn't particularly efficient.
所以绝大部分计算机的除法就是
So most computer processors today have divide as one of the instructions
ALU可以执行的指令
that the ALU can perform in hardware.
显然这个额外的电路让ALU的设计更庞大和复杂
Of course, this extra circuitry makes the ALU bigger and more complicated to design,
同时性能也更强 这是复杂度与速度的折衷
but also more capable - a complexity-for-speed trade-off
计算机历史上很多次用到
that has been made many times in computing history.
例如 现代计算机处理器对图形运算 解码压缩视频 加密文件等操作
For instance, modern computer processors now have special circuits for things like
都有特殊的电路
graphics operations, decoding compressed video, and encrypting files
如果用标准的运算
- all of which are operations that would take many many many clock cycles
这些运算需要很多很多时钟周期
to perform with standard operations.
你可能听过带有MMX 3DNow! 或者 SSE
You may have even heard of processors with MMX, 3DNow!, or SSE.
【注：MMX是Intel推出的多媒体增强指令集(Multi Media Extension)，优点是增加了
处理器关于多媒体方面的处理能力，缺点是占用浮点数寄存器进行运算，AMD在此基础上
发展出3D Now!指令集，3D Now!发布一年后，Intel在MMX基础上发展出SSE
（Streaming SIMD Extensions）指令集，用来取代MMX】
这些都是带有额外高级电路的处理器 能执行额外的高级指令
These are processors with additional, fancy circuits that allow them to execute additional,
针对于游戏和加密
fancy instructions - for things like gaming and encryption.
这些扩展指令集不断扩大
These extensions to the instruction set have grown, and grown over time, and once people
一旦人们写的程序用到它们 就难以移除了
have written programs to take advantage of them, it's hard to remove them.
结果就是指令集越来越大
So instruction sets tend to keep getting larger and larger
由于向后兼容保存了所有旧的操作码
keeping all the old opcodes around for backwards compatibility.
Intel4004 第一个真正的集成CPU 它有46条指令
The Intel 4004, the first truly integrated CPU, had 46 instructions
这足够搭建一个功能完备的计算机
- which was enough to build a fully functional computer.
但是现代计算机有几千条不同的指令
But a modern computer processor has thousands of different instructions,
这利用了各种各样精巧复杂的内部电路
which utilize all sorts of clever and complex internal circuitry.
现在高时钟频率和高级指令集引向了另一个问题
Now, high clock speeds and fancy instruction sets lead to another problem
如何把数据足够快的输入输出CPU
- getting data in and out of the CPU quickly enough.
就像是有一个大功率的蒸汽机火车头 但无铲进煤速度跟不上
It's like having a powerful steam locomotive, but no way to shovel in coal fast enough.
这种情况下瓶颈就在RAM
In this case, the bottleneck is RAM.
RAM通常是CPU外部的内存模块
RAM is typically a memory module that lies outside the CPU.
这意味着数据需要通过数据线传输进出RAM
This means that data has to be transmitted to and from RAM along sets of data wires,
这里的线叫做总线
called a bus.
总线可能不过几厘米长 而且电子信号
This bus might only be a few centimeters long, and remember those electrical signals are
以接近光速传播 但是当你以GHz速度运行
traveling near the speed of light, but when you are operating at gigahertz speeds –
那就是几十亿分之一秒 即使这么小的延迟也变得麻烦
that's billionths of a second – even this small delay starts to become problematic.
【注：延迟指电信号在总线传递的时间，对CPU来说，这个传递时间就是延迟】
RAM自身查询地址 获取数据
It also takes time for RAM itself to look up the address, retrieve the data,
配置输出
and configure itself for output.
所以一个从RAM加载的指令就得花上几十个时钟循环来完成
So a 'load from RAM' instruction might take dozens of clock cycles to complete,
这段时间里处理器就空闲着 等待数据
and during this time the processor is just sitting there idly waiting for the data.
一个解决办法是把一小块RAM放在CPU里 叫做缓存
One solution is to put a little piece of RAM right on the CPU - called a cache.
处理器里并没有很大空间 所以大部分缓存只是kB或
There isn't a lot of space on a processor's chip, so most caches are just kilobytes or
可能是MB 而RAM则是GB
maybe megabytes in size, where RAM is usually gigabytes.
添加缓存是一个巧妙地加速方法
Having a cache speeds things up in a clever way.
当CPU从RAM里获取一个内存地址时
When the CPU requests a memory location from RAM,
RAM不只可以传输一个数据 而是一整块数据
the RAM can transmit not just one single value, but a whole block of data.
这只需要多花费一点时间 就可以把数据块存到缓存里
This takes only a little bit more time, but it allows this data block to be saved into the cache.
这很有帮助
This tends to be really useful
因为常常连续排列和处理计算机数据
because computer data is often arranged and processed sequentially.
例如 假设处理器在合计餐馆的日销量
For example, let's say the processor is totaling up daily sales for a restaurant.
一开始从RAM的内存地址100获取第一笔交易
It starts by fetching the first transaction from RAM at memory location 100.
RAM不仅是发送一个数据 而是一块数据
The RAM, instead of sending back just that one value, sends a block of data,
从内存地址100到200都复制到缓存里
from memory location 100 through 200, which are then all copied into the cache.
当处理器要求下一条交易加到营业总额时
Now, when the processor requests the next transaction to add to its running total,
对于地址101的数据 缓存就会说噢 我这里已经有了这个数据
the value at address 101, the cache will say 'Oh, I've already got that value right here,
我可以立刻给你
so I can give it to you right away!'
就不必再去RAM获取了
And there's no need to go all the way to RAM.
因为缓存离处理器很近
Because the cache is so close to the processor,
它通常可以在一个时钟周期内提供数据——不需要等待
it can typically provide the data in a single clock cycle - no waiting required.
这大大加速了运行
This speeds things up tremendously
原高于每次都来来回回从RAM传输
over having to go back and forth to RAM every single time.
像这样如果需要的RAM数据已经被储存到缓存里 叫做缓存命中
When data requested in RAM is already stored in the cache like this it's called a cache hit
如果不在 就得去RAM
and if the data requested isn't in the cache, so you have to go to RAM,
叫做缓存未命中
it's a called a cache miss.
缓存也可以作为暂存空间 储存中间数据
The cache can also be used like a scratch space, storing intermediate values
当执行更长更复杂的计算时
when performing a longer, or more complicated calculation.
继续餐馆的例子 这时处理器完成了总计
Continuing our restaurant example, let's say the processor has finished totaling up
一天的销量 然后要把结果储存到内存地址150中
all of the sales for the day, and wants to store the result in memory address 150.
跟前面一样不是直接存到RAM里
Like before, instead of going back all the way to RAM to save that value,
可以存在缓存里复制一份 储存的速度很快
it can be stored in cached copy, which is faster to save to,
其他计算如果要用到获取也更快
and also faster to access later if more calculations are needed.
但是这引发了一个有趣的问题
But this introduces an interesting problem
现在缓存中复制的数据和真实RAM中不一样
- the cache's copy of the data is now different to the real version stored in RAM.
这种不匹配需要记录下来 这样某一时刻可以同步
This mismatch has to be recorded, so that at some point everything can get synced up.
为此 缓存给每一块内存一个特殊的标志 叫做
For this purpose, the cache has a special flag for each block of memory it stores, called
脏位 这大概是计算机学家创造的最棒的术语
the dirty bit - which might just be the best term computer scientists have ever invented.
一般来说缓存满了就同步
Most often this synchronization happens when the cache is full,
但如果处理器要求获取一块新的内存
but a new block of memory is being requested by the processor.
缓存在清除旧的内存块释放空间的之前 检查脏位
Before the cache erases the old block to free up space, it checks its dirty bit,
如果标识是脏（不匹配） 原先的数据块就写回RAM 然后载入新的数据块
and if it's dirty, the old block of data is written back to RAM before loading in the new block.
另一个提升CPU性能的办法是指令流水线
Another trick to boost CPU performance is called instruction pipelining.
想象你要洗一整个旅馆的床单
Imagine you have to wash an entire hotel's worth of sheets,
但你只有一台洗衣机和一台烘干机
but you've only got one washing machine and one dryer.
一种选择是连续工作：
One option is to do it all sequentially:
把一批床单放入洗衣机 等待30分钟完成
put a batch of sheets in the washer and wait 30 minutes for it to finish.
再把湿床单拿出来放入烘干机
Then take the wet sheets out and put them in the dryer and
再等30分钟完成
wait another 30 minutes for that to finish.
这样1小时可以洗一批衣服
This allows you to do one batch of sheets every hour.
注：如果你有30分钟烘完一批的烘干机
Side note: if you have a dryer that can dry a load of laundry in 30 minutes,
请在评论区告诉我品牌和型号
please tell me the brand and model in the comments,
我用的烘干机最低也要90分钟
because I'm living with 90 minute dry times, minimum.
但是尽管有这个神奇的烘干机 你还可以加快更多
But, even with this magic clothes dryer, you can speed things up even more
如果你同时操作
if you parallelize your operation.
跟前面一样开始时把一批床单放进洗衣机
As before, you start off putting one batch of sheets in the washer.
等待30分钟完成
You wait 30 minutes for it to finish.
然后拿出湿床单 放进烘干机
Then you take the wet sheets out and put them in the dryer.
不过这一次 不仅仅等待烘干机30分钟完成
But this time, instead of just waiting 30 minutes for the dryer to finish,
你同时开始处理另一批床单 放进洗衣机
you simultaneously start another load in the washing machine.
现在两个机器同时进行
Now you've got both machines going at once.
等待30分钟 现在有一批完成 有一批完成一半
Wait 30 minutes, and one batch is now done, one batch is half done,
而另外一批正准备开始
and another is ready to go in.
这有效的加倍了吞吐量
This effectively doubles your throughput.
处理器设置可以采用同样的思想
Processor designs can apply the same idea.
第7集中 示例处理器连续的执行了取指-译码-执行的周期
In episode 7, our example processor performed the fetch-decode-execute cycle sequentially
并不断循环
and in a continuous loop:
取指-译码-执行 取指-译码-执行 取指-译码-执行 等等
Fetch-decode-execute, fetch-decode-execute, fetch-decode-execute, and so on.
这意味着设计执行1条指令需要3个时钟周期
This meant our design required three clock cycles to execute one instruction.
但这三个阶段使用CPU的不同部分
But each of these stages uses a different part of the CPU,
这样就有机会同时运行了
meaning there is an opportunity to parallelize!
当一个指令开始执行 下一条指令就可以开始译码
While one instruction is getting executed, the next instruction could be getting decoded,
再下一条就可以从内存取指
and the instruction beyond that fetched from memory.
所有的步骤可以重叠
All of these separate processes can overlap
这样CPU的所有部分在任何时间都在工作
so that all parts of the CPU are active at any given time.
在这个流水线设计中每个时钟周期执行一条指令
In this pipelined design, an instruction is executed every single clock cycle
使得吞吐量增大到三倍
which triples the throughput.
但是就像是用到了缓存 这样可能导致麻烦的问题
But just like with caching this can lead to some tricky problems.
一个很大的风险是指令间的相关
A big hazard is a dependency in the instructions.
比如 你可能要获取那些当前正在执行的指令
For example, you might fetch something that the currently executing instruction is just
即将修改的数据 那么你就会把旧数据留在流水线上
about to modify, which means you'll end up with the old value in the pipeline.
为了弥补这个缺陷 流水线处理器需要提前寻找数据的相关关系
To compensate for this, pipelined processors have to look ahead for data dependencies,
如果需要停下流水线来避免问题
and if necessary, stall their pipelines to avoid problems.
高档的处理器 例如笔记本和智能手机里的
High end processors, like those found in laptops and smartphones,
更加高级 能动态的记录相关的指令
go one step further and can dynamically reorder instructions with dependencies
以最小化流水线的停止 让它保持活动
in order to minimize stalls and keep the pipeline moving,
叫做超限额运算
which is called out-of-order execution.
可以想象 完成这个的电路异常复杂
As you might imagine, the circuits that figure this all out are incredibly complicated.
尽管这样 流水线还是极其高效
Nonetheless, pipelining is tremendously effective
几乎被所有的处理器采用
and almost all processors implement it today.
另一个大的风险是条件跳转指令
Another big hazard are conditional jump instructions
上一集说到了负数跳转指令
- we talked about one example, a JUMP_NEGATIVE, last episode.
这些指令可以根据数值改变程序的流程
These instructions can change the execution flow of a program depending on a value.
简单的流水线处理器遇到跳转指令会停止很久
A simple pipelined processor will perform a long stall when it sees a jump instruction,
等待数值最终确定
waiting for the value to be finalized.
只有跳转结果明确了 处理去才开始重新填充流水线
Only once the jump outcome is known, does the processor start refilling its pipeline.
但是这可能造成长时间延迟
But, this can produce long delays,
所以高端处理器对此也有技巧
so high-end processors have some tricks to deal with this problem too.
想象即将的跳转指令是路上的岔口——分支
Imagine an upcoming jump instruction as a fork in a road - a branch.
高级的CPU 猜测会走哪条路 然后开始基于这个猜测
Advanced CPUs guess which way they are going to go, and start filling their pipeline with
填充流水线 这个技术叫做预测执行
instructions based off that guess – a technique called speculative execution.
当跳转指令解决后 如果CPU预测正确
When the jump instruction is finally resolved, if the CPU guessed correctly,
那么流水线已经装载了正确的指令
then the pipeline is already full of the correct instructions
可以不用停留的运行下去
and it can motor along without delay.
但是 如果CPU预测错误
However, if the CPU guessed wrong, it has to discard all its speculative results
就会刷新流水线 有点像你错过了路口转弯就必须掉头
and perform a pipeline flush - sort of like when you miss a turn and have to do a u-turn
回到正确路线上 让GPS不再发出警告
to get back on route, and stop your GPS's insistent shouting.
为了减小刷新的影响 CPU制造者开发了
To minimize the effects of these flushes, CPU manufacturers have developed
复杂的方法预测哪个要走向哪个分支 叫做分支预测
sophisticated ways to guess which way branches will go, called branch prediction.
不同于随机猜测如今的处理器都可以达到90%以上的正确率
Instead of being a 50/50 guess, today's processors can often guess with over 90% accuracy!
理想情况下 流水线可以每一时钟周期完成一个指令
In an ideal case, pipelining lets you complete one instruction every single clock cycle,
但是超标量处理器更高级
but then superscalar processors came along
它可以每时钟周期执行超过一条指令
which can execute more than one instruction per clock cycle.
即使是流水线设计在执行阶段
During the execute phase even in a pipelined design,
处理器某个区域都可能是完全空闲的
whole areas of the processor might be totally idle.
例如 执行一个获取内存中数值的指令
For example, while executing an instruction that fetches a value from memory,
ALU就会等待着 什么也不做
the ALU is just going to be sitting there, not doing a thing.
那么为什么不同时取指 译码几个指令 如果可以
So why not fetch-and-decode several instructions at once, and whenever possible,
同时执行所有利用CPU不同部分的指令
execute instructions that require different parts of the CPU all at the same time?
不过我们可以更进一步 给常用的指令增加重复的电路
But we can take this one step further and add duplicate circuitry for popular instructions.
例如 很多处理器有4 8或者更多同样的ALU
For example, many processors will have four, eight or more identical ALUs,
他们可以同步执行很多数学指令
so they can execute many mathematical instructions all in parallel!
好了 目前我们讨论的主要是优化单个指令流的执行吞吐量
OK, the techniques we've discussed so far primarily optimize the execution throughput
另一个方法是
of a single stream of instructions, but another way to increase performance
用多核处理器同时运行多条指令流
is to run several streams of instructions at once with multi-core processors.
你可能听过双核或四核处理器
You might have heard of dual core or quad core processors.
这意味着单个CPU芯片中有多个独立的处理单元
This means there are multiple independent processing units inside of a single CPU chip.
很多方面来看 这类似于有多个独立的CPU
In many ways, this is very much like having multiple separate CPUs,
但是由于他们紧密的集成在一起 可以分享一些资源
but because they're tightly integrated, they can share some resources,
比如分享缓存 使多个核可以处理共享的计算结果
like cache, allowing the cores to work together on shared computations.
但是仅仅多核也不够用
But, when more cores just isn't enough,
你还可以构建多个独立CPU的计算机
you can build computers with multiple independent CPUs!
高端计算机 像是从油管数据中心传输这个视频的服务器
High end computers, like the servers streaming this video from YouTube’s datacenter,
常常需要额外的功率保证传输流畅
often need the extra horsepower to keep it silky smooth
因为数百人同时在观看
for the hundreds of people watching simultaneously.
现在双核或四核处理器的配置最常见
Two- and four-processor configuration are the most common right now,
但是有时候那样的处理能力还不够
but every now and again even that much processing power isn't enough.
因此人们志向更大了 建造出了超级计算机
So we humans get extra ambitious and build ourselves a supercomputer!
如果你要做巨大的计算
If you're looking to do some really monster calculations
像是模拟宇宙的形成
– like simulating the formation of the universe
你就需要非常大的计算能力
- you'll need some pretty serious compute power.
笔记本上多几个处理器并不能搞定
A few extra processors in a desktop computer just isn't going to cut it.
你需要很多处理器
You're going to need a lot of processors.
不 还要更多 很多很多
No.. no... even more than that. A lot more!
这个视频制作的时候 世界上最快的计算机位于
When this video was made, the world's fastest computer was located
中国无锡国家超算中心
in The National Supercomputing Center in Wuxi, China.
神威 太湖之光 有难以想象的40,960个CPU 每个有256个核
The Sunway TaihuLight contains a brain-melting 40,960 CPUs, each with 256 cores!
也就是总计超过一千万的核 每个核以1.45GHz频率运行
That's over ten million cores in total... and each one of those cores runs at 1.45 gigahertz.
总计 这个机器可以处理93夸克 即93千万亿的
In total, this machine can process 93 Quadrillion - that's 93 million-billions
总计 这个机器可以处理93夸克
浮点数学运算每秒 记作FLOPS
- floating point math operations per second, knows as FLOPS.
相信我 那是很高的每秒浮点运算次数
And trust me, that's a lot of FLOPS!!
没有说明它是否能以最高的环境运行孤岛危机 不过我想是可以
No word on whether it can run Crysis at max settings, but I suspect it might.
总之 计算机处理器多年来不仅变快了
So long story short, not only have computer processors gotten a lot faster over the years,
还更复杂了 应用了各种各样巧妙地技巧
but also a lot more sophisticated, employing all sorts of clever tricks to squeeze out
挤出了更多的没时钟周期的计算量
more and more computation per clock cycle.
我们的工作就是利用这样极好的处理能力做酷的有用的事
Our job is to wield that incredible processing power to do cool and useful things.
这就是编程的本质 我们下一集开始讨论
That's the essence of programming, which we'll start discussing next episode.
再见
See you next week.
阿尔法小分队荣誉译制
翻：@ErrorEnvyEnchant 校：@Auriance 压制：@Mihael_Ho
长期招募 详情见微博置顶@阿尔法小分队科教组